A Guide to the Records of the Central Virginia Training Center, circa 1909-2000s
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Central Virginia Training Center,
circa 1909-2000s
The Library of Virginia
41282, 50941
Central Virginia Training Center.
25 cu. ft. (25 boxes)
13 v.
Part of Record Group 38 (Virginia Dept. of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services).
This collection has been processed using minimal processing standards: the original arrangement has been maintained, the container list is brief and simple, and the records have not been refoldered and fasteners have not been removed.
As of September 11, 2019, medical records will be open 125 years after the date of creation or after date closed, whichever is later. The Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) requires that individually identifiable health information of a decedent be protected for 50 years following the date of death of the individual (45 CFR 164.502(f)).
Protected health information (PHI) as defined under the Privacy Regulations issued under the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) includes, but is not limited to, personally identifiable information such as names, addresses, and social security numbers. Restricted material may include, but is not limited to: patient lists, patient admission registers, treatment registers, medical record files, sterilization records, and patient photographs. Please contact Archives Research Services for further information.
Acquisition Information
Accession 41282 was transferred by the Central Virginia Training Center, 06/30/2004
Virginia. -- Dept. of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services
Lynchburg Training School and Hospital.
Mental health services -- Virginia.
Mental retardation facilities -- Virginia.
Registers (lists) -- aat.
State government records -- Virginia. -- aat.
Contains records, circa 1909-2000s, of the Central Virginia Training Center in Lynchburg, Virginia. Includes correspondence, newsletters, operating room registers, sterilization records, publications, reports, photographs, and scrapbooks, among others.
Contents List
- Series I. Patient Records, 1929-1994.
  Restricted: patient records that are less than 125 years old. Contains sterilization registers, operating room records, resident movement ledgers, posting sheets, and discharges. The sterilization registers contain the name of the patient; the dates upon which legal papers were served on the patient and, if necessary, the patient’s parents; the date the patient appeared before the board; the decision of the board; and the date of the sterilization. The operating room records contain an entry for every surgery performed in the Training Center’s operating room, which includes both sterilizations and other surgeries; there is also one ledger of staff meeting minutes from 1945, which includes decisions made by hospital staff regarding the sterilization of patients. The resident movement ledgers include the names of patients and their dates of parole, return from parole, discharge, death, and escape as well as a daily count of the number of patients in the facility. The posting sheets contain a daily count of the number of patients in the facility, and the loose discharges contain the names of the patient and their date of discharge. Finally, the miscellaneous medical records contain staff notes from 1970 and 1971, sterilization reports from 1958 and 1970-1973, and other miscellaneous records.
  - Sterilization register, 1929-1959. (Box 1)
  - Photocopy of sterilization register, 1929-1959. (Box 27)
  - Sterilization register, 1930-1959. (Volume 7)
  - Sterilization register, 1959-1973. (Volume 8)
  - Operating Room Records, 1930-1958. (Box 2)
  - Operating Room Records and Staff Board Meeting Minutes, 1944-1945, 1958-1979. (Box 3)
  - Resident Movement Ledger, 1939-1960. (Volume 1)
  - Resident Movement Ledger, 1960-1963. (Volume 2)
  - Resident Movement Ledger, 1963-1971. (Volume 3)
  - Resident Movement Ledger, 1971-1976. (Volume 4)
  - Resident Movement Ledger, 1976-1981. (Volume 5)
  - Resident Movement Ledger, 1981-1994. (Volume 6)
  - Posting sheets, 1939-1963. (Volume 13)
  - Discharges, 1950s-1970s circa. (Volume 12)
  - Admissions registers, 1937-1975. (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous records, 1952-1973. (Box 5)
- Series II. Administrative Records, 1909-2000s circa.
  Includes correspondence, subject files, property records, scrapbooks, photographs, and other material relating to the operation of Central Virginia Training Center.
- Series III. Publications, 1909-2000s circa.
  Includes staff and patient newsletters, annual reports, theses, disserations, and other publications created or collected by the Central Virginia Training Center.